<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>bkardell.com rss feed</title>
        <link>http://bkardell.com/</link>
        <description>Just the bkardell.com rss feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:45:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
        <generator>awesome mix</generator>
        <image>
            <title>bkardell.com rss feed</title>
            <url>http://bkardell.com/profile.jpg</url>
            <link>http://bkardell.com/</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2018, Brian Kardell</copyright>
        <atom:link href="https://bkardell.com/blog/feed.atom" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Secret Life of Custom Elements]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/SecretLifeOfCustomElements.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/SecretLifeOfCustomElements.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Twenty years ago last month, Google published an analysis of "slightly over a billion documents," a snapshot of the web that helped shape the early direction of HTML5. It followed a lineage of smaller, more personal studies — individuals poking at the web to answer some narrow question, often with datasets that would easily fit on a thumb drive today. For about half those two decades, I’ve been arguing that we need more study of the web, not less. The platform evolves faster than our understanding of it, and the only way to know what the web actually is — not what we imagine it to be — is to look.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	<h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">The Secret Life of Custom Elements</h1>

<p class="segue">Twenty years ago last month, Google published <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060203035414/http://code.google.com/webstats/index.html">an analysis of "slightly over a billion documents,"</a> a snapshot of the web that helped shape the early direction of HTML5. It followed a lineage of smaller, more personal studies — individuals poking at the web to answer some narrow question, often with datasets that would easily fit on a thumb drive today. For about half those two decades, I’ve been arguing that we need <strong>more</strong> study of the web, not less. The platform evolves faster than our understanding of it, and the only way to know what the web actually is — not what we imagine it to be — is to look.</p>
<p>Every month the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Archive">HTTP Archive</a> quietly captures a snapshot of the web as it actually exists—not the idealized web that we hope for, but the messy, improvised, duct‑taped reality of millions of sites in the wild.  I’ve been collecting and studying these elements for the last six years. </p>
<p>This new dataset is the largest I’ve ever worked with: Billions of pages, hundreds of thousands of distinct non-standard element names, and a long tail that stretches into places no standards body has ever seriously examined. And unlike the Google study, which looked for patterns in class names, this dataset captures the long tail of non‑standard elements — the names people invent for actual elements when the platform doesn’t give them what they need.</p>
<p>What emerges is a portrait of the web as it is lived: messy, inventive, repetitive, global, and full of reinvention. It’s also a mirror held up to the platform itself.</p>
<p>But, it's also much more complex to study than I could have imagined a decade ago, and I really wish that the W3C (and member orgs which include academia) had taken up the charge to begin to figure out how to really study the web and use that information to inform standards work.</p>
<section class="sectioning">
<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">What's difficult about it...</h2>
<p>One problem is that the dataset itself has some fairly extreme bias.  The crawl doesn't hit anything that isn't on the public internet - that means it excludes intranets which are <em>massive</em>.  In fact, most of my career was spent working on intranets.  The crawl captures only home pages, plus the target of whatever it interprets as the largest link on that page.  It also can't get to anything that requires login - which means that for a site like twitter or bluesky or mastodon, you're going to get something very unrepresentative of any of those.  So, one challenge I'd love to see us trying to tackle is how to get even better data representation.  It's hard to "pave cowpaths" if they're in a country we can't even see into.</p>
<p>Initially I had this idea that we could watch for the adoption of tags - imagining that we'd get some that would become <em>very</em> popular, just like we did with JavaScript libraries and frameworks.  However, it turns out that this is not the signal it might first appear to be.  An element appearing in tens of thousands or even hundreds of thousands of pages is often simply because they are part of a larger successful system.  If Wix or Shopify create some custom elements that work behind the WYSIWYG tooling, and lots of people use it to create their pages - then suddenly that element gets very very popular - even if it isn't actually particularly good.  In fact, we can see shifts in the data where the teams themselves changed their minds and another version supplants the first very quickly because it's simply internal.</p>
<p>Then, I thought that perhaps what we can do with the dataset instead, is to squint at it and look a little more abstractly at what people are naming their elements and see if people are re-solving similar problems.  Do we find, for example, multiple non-standard element names that appear to be about tabs?  Yes! Clearly that is indicative that we need a native element, right?  <em>Maybe</em>.  It's a bit more nuanced than that.  Here are the most commonly re-created/repeated non-standard element themes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Navigation  </li>
<li>Headers and footers  </li>
<li>Carousels and sliders</li>
<li>Modals  </li>
<li>Search bars  </li>
<li>Product cards  </li>
<li>Login forms  </li>
<li>Cookie banners  </li>
<li>Accordions  </li>
<li>Tabs   </li>
<li>Toasts  </li>
<li>Breadcrumbs</li>
</ul>
<p>While we don't have several of these in standard HTML, we <em>do</em> have native <code>&lt;header&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;footer&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;nav&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code>, and <code>&lt;search&gt;</code> elements, and even accordions via the <code>name</code> attribute of <code>&lt;details&gt;</code>.  And yet, the wild still contains hundreds or thousands of custom elements with names like <code>&lt;app-header&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;site-footer&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;main-nav&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;modal-dialog&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;search-box&gt;</code>, and <code>&lt;accordion-panel&gt;</code>.</p>
<p>Native primitives may exist, but not at the same level of abstraction as these.  <code>&lt;header&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;footer&gt;</code> in HTML are structural, not behavioral.  <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code> is behavioral, but not styled.  <code>&lt;search&gt;</code> exists, but doesn’t solve autocomplete, filtering, or results.</p>
<p>So developers build those - and, if you stop and think about it, not all non-standard elements are equally as undesirable.  Many of them will be simple decorations or thin wrappers that <em>do</em> use their native counterparts.  Where there is definitely some interesting thing to study is where there is clear generic need where the platform doesn't provide anything close.  Above, tabs, for example.</p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">
	<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Observations..</h2>
<p>Here are many observations from the data, in no real particular order of importance.</p>
	<section class="sectioning">
		<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Forms and Inputs: Tweaked, Wrapped, and Re‑Wrapped</h3>
<p>Forms and inputs are a great example of the constant re-invention I just described.  Sometimes it's because the native element is insufficient, but that's not <em>necessarily</em> the case.  In some cases they're just slight wrappers.  Among them are lots and lots of "pickers" and "selecters" that show up...</p>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;custom-select&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;date-picker&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;variant-picker&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;quantity-selector&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
<p>There is already a lot of ongoing work to make native form elements (including selects) require less code and just be more stylable and flexible, and the data at least suggests that such efforts will be very welcome.</p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">
<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Hidden Machinery</h3>
<p>A surprising number of elements aren’t UI components at all. They’re runtime markers:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;ng-container&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;router-outlet&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;astro-island&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;ion-router-outlet&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;next-route-announcer&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These exist because frameworks need declarative boundaries for hydration, routing, rendering or template expansion. I suppose it is debatable wither these are an indicator of “missing HTML features”, or just how much.  </p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">

<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Carousels (and sliders... and toasts)</h3>
<p>I don't love carousels, but it's hard to deny that they are popular.  There are <em>dozens</em> of distinct and identifiable carousel/slider elements in the dataset and they appear <em>a lot</em>.  I really dislike a few bits of Google's attempt to make CSS-only carousels possible, but it's pretty clear why they chose to tackle that problem. I guess it is worth stressing again the bias in the dataset here - if there is a page I most expect to see a carousel, it is exactly the primary one the archive crawls.  So, while it is the most popular in the dataset, I don't know that it is the most popular all-around. You can see why Google winds up with their proposals though, toasts are on that top list too.</p>
</section>

<section class="sectioning">
<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Structural semantics?</h3>
<p>There are a few broad categories where the main point seems to be "semantics". That is, very often many of these don't actually <em>do</em> anything, beyond provide some hooks, mainly for styling.  They aren't actually even custom elements sometimes (or maybe even often) - just non-standard elements. </p>
<section class="sectioning">
<h4 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3.5rem;">e-commerce</h4>
<p>Dozens of these surround e-commerce.  There are tens of thousands of sites that use elements with names (and variants).</p>
<details>
<summary>Product &amp; merchandising</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;product-card&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-title&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-price&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-rating&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-variant&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-gallery&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-description&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;product-badge&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>
<details>
<summary>Pricing &amp; money</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;price-money&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;sale-price&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;compare-at-price&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;discount-amount&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;currency-display&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>
<details>
<summary>Inventory &amp; availability</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;stock-status&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;pickup-availability&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;delivery-estimate&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;inventory-level&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>

<details>
<summary>Cart &amp; checkout</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;cart-items&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;cart-count&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;checkout-button&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;order-summary&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>

<p>Very interestingly they are often used alongside actual machine readable semantics via jsonLD in the same markup.  </p>
<p>While the vast majority of these elements appear because of common tooling, the fact that there are dozens of variants of similar names appearing on smaller numbers of sites indicates there is something widely interesting here. It's hard to say what it is other than that it would be nice to have a common structural semantic that would work for both purposes.</p>
<p>I guess the biggest surprise here is that if it's true, why hasn't such a thing arisen already? It is entirely within the community's power to develop such a thing.  Perhaps the answer is that there is just so much variance it isn't easily plausible.  Maybe templating would somehow allow us to achieve a common pattern which achieved this based on the shared jsonLD semantics.</p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">
<h4 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3.5rem;">Publishing &amp; Editorial Semantics</h4>
<p>CMSes and news sites often invent tags for editorial structure, and many of these are sticking around.</p>
<details>
<summary>Content structure</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;article-header&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-summary&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-author&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-date&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-tags&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-tag&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;article-category&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;byline&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;dateline&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;pullquote&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;footnote&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>
<details>
<summary>Taxonomy</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;tag-list&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;category-label&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;topic-header&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>
<p>These reflect the needs of journalism and long‑form content.</p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">
	<h4 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3.5rem;">Social &amp; Community Semantics</h4>
<p>These show up in comment systems, forums, and social platforms.</p>
	
<details>
	<summary>User‑generated content</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;comment&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-list&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-item&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-author&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-content&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-date&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;comment-form&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>

<details>
<summary>Identity</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;user-avatar&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;user-name&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;profile-card&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These encode relationships and interactions, not UI patterns.</p>
</details>

<details>
<summary>Events</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;event-date&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;event-location&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;event-schedule&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;event-details&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Again, these are domain objects, not widgets - and they have well established schema.org or microformats as well. </p>
</details>

<details>
<summary>Invoicing</summary>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;invoice&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;invoice-line&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;invoice-total&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;invoice-summary&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
</details>

<p>Before the web came along, there were already national and international standards around electronically trading informtation like invoices - and when XML was sold, invoices were a common example.  Here we are again.</p>
</section>

</section>

<section class="sectioning">
	<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">"Namespaced" Elements</h3>

<p>Several elements like `o:p`, `rdf:rdf`, `dc:format`, `cc:work`, `fb:like`, `g:plusone` appear in the top 100.  These basically were thinking of an XHTML future (namespacing) that never really arrived.  However, HTML has always allowed it - so that's just the tag name.  In many ways, it's just as good.  Interestingly, these may be some of the better examples of what I'd like to see happen - they are widely understood.</p>

<p>Conversely, while hugely successful, the share buttons are more an indication of a desire than something we could actually standardize in precisely that way.  They also point to a desire _in time_.  Google Plus doesn't even exist anymore, `fb:like` is from a time when Facebook was at the top of the most interesting places to be.  Maybe one of the things we've learned is that this is way handier to do at the browser/OS levels?  I suppose the Web Share API was a part of thinking how we'd deal with this.</p>

<p>The fact that they both still appear so much is also kind of an indication of age of the page and slow replacement of underlying tools.</p>

</section>

<section class="sectioning">
	<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Typos, Encoding Errors, and the Weird Stuff</h3>
<p>One of the most delightful parts of the dataset is the long tail of what are almost certainly just typos:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;prodcut-card&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;navgation&gt;</code></li>
<li><code>&lt;contianer&gt;</code></li>
</ul>
<p>The fact that these can appear on tens of thousands of sites because they are part of common tooling helps re-enforce that not every non-standard element is a signal. :)</p>
</section>
<section class="sectioning">
<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">In conclusion...</h3>
<p>I wish that I could say "Ah ha - the data says very clearly that <em>these</em> are the specific things we should definitely 'just write down' now" in the way that I imagined a decade ago, but I don't think we're there yet.  I guess if I had to give three things I'd like to see happen from here they'd be:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>We need lots more effort in thinking about how to study these things.  I would love to see real investment in this space.  This year, at last, the W3C is hiring someone to study the web.  I'm not yet sure what that looks like but I look forward to trying to discuss more with them.</p>
</li>
<li><p>We need a real community effort - an <a href="https://ul.org/about/our-history/">Underwriters Labs</a> for custom elements, with participation and funding from orgs with money.  We don't necessarily need "the one true tabs" as much as we need a place to find what I expect will be a very few sets of tabs as custom elements which we can trust like we trust native elements.  Given a little bit of time, I have faith that this will naturally sort itself into a few 'winners'.  </p>
</li>
<li><p>That community effort might also include things which won't ever have native implmentations, but which lay down some kind of light semantic meaning or compound styling structure that we all begin to agree on - like product cards or breadcrumbs.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A lot of this is pretty adjacent/close to the ideas behind OpenUI and it's possible some of this could just happen there.  However, due mainly to limits and participation, OpenUI has really not really produced custom elements or worked to somehow list or grade and promote them (though we did study them quite a bit in the tabs research).  The effort led by Brad Frost to think about a "global design system" in particular might be closer to some of these ideas.</p>
</section>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Standards Queues]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/Queues.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/Queues.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The hardest part of web standards isn’t even the technology — it’s the queues. And that’s the real problem I keep coming back to.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	<h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Standards Queues</h1>
<p class="segue">The hardest part of web standards isn’t even the technology — it’s the queues. And that’s the real problem I keep coming back to.</p>

	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Pools, Queues, and Bottlenecks</h2>
		<p>As programmers, we’re familiar with these kinds of problems: if things enter faster than they leave, they back up. We often need to prioritize among the backlog. The standards process is like several of those queues stacked together.</p>
		<p>Ideas enter the system far faster than they leave — and they can come from anywhere. But to progress, you need implementers. They are finite, already busy, and often advancing their own priorities. On top of that, every proposal competes for wide review in privacy, security, architecture, accessibility, and internationalization. Each of those specialties is even more finite, even more busy, and even more backed up.</p>
		<p>So an idea lands in hundreds — even thousands — of inboxes, waiting for attention. We might not even notice it as it whips past among all the others. Even if we do, it might just get starred in email or left open in a tab for “later.” Sometimes that idea is a book, or an explainer, or suddenly has 20 replies. Instead of needing five minutes to read and consider, it becomes intimidating.</p>
		<p>At some point it just sits. It might wait weeks, months, or even years before someone comments. Why? Because everyone has jobs with other tasks. The queues are full.</p>
		<p>And the longer it sits, the more things change around it. The more it unloads from memory. The more intimidating it becomes to return to. It has to get through a whole lot of asynchronous back-and-forth between implementers, spec writers, and test writers before reaching baseline usability.</p>
		<p>Along the way, if coordination isn’t strong (and historically it hasn’t been), once work is invested it’s hard to throw away. It’s hard to propose breaking changes or add stop energy.</p>
	</section>
	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Real Impacts</h2>
		<p>This is why something like :focus-visible can take seven years. Realistically, it required only a few days of effective discussion. The tests and development weren’t that hard.</p>
		<p>The hard part was agreeing on what it should do and which tests it should pass. Most of that difficulty came from the fact that you couldn’t get everyone to sit down and focus concurrently. Implementations — and thus real focus — were years apart.</p>
	</section>
	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Checking Fitness</h2>
		<p>Getting “unstuck” isn’t just about moving something forward. One major appeal of the standards process is wide review, but for this to work we need ways for things to fail early enough to shift efforts.</p>
		<p>Sometimes failure happens after months or even years. That’s frustrating and demoralizing. It’s like standing in a long DMV line, inching forward, only to discover at the end that you’re in the wrong building.</p>
		<p>All of this is made worse by the fact that queues keep getting fuller.</p>
	</section>
	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Things that help</h2>
		<section class="sectioning">
			<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Interop</h3>
			<p>The Interop project illustrates the very end of the process, and in many ways the simplest.</p>
			<p>Without intervention, each implementer historically built their own priority queue from all possible shortcomings of their browser engine. There’s a huge pool of things to choose from. I’ve written before about how WPT and the dashboard aren’t the best way to view this, but there are currently almost 23k subtests that fail in every browser (or almost 11k that fail and aren’t marked tentative).</p>
			<p>Interop coordinates efforts to choose an achievable set of things from this gigantic pool that meet strict criteria: all that’s left is implementation work. It’s been hugely successful because it ensures delivery. It also helps us deliver early when people are excited about common priorities. In those cases, the impact is huge — we can go from mostly words to three interoperable implementations in one year. Amazing.</p>
			<p>Still, every year a huge number of things remain in the pool that we can’t afford to take up. The pool keeps growing.</p>
		</section>
		<section class="sectioning">
			<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Joint Meetings</h3>
			<p>The WHATWG has started holding regular joint meetings with groups like OpenUI and CSSWG. This is valuable because it allows the right people to agree on an agenda and discuss directly, rather than leaving issues to sit unnoticed or requiring endless pings for attention.</p>
			<p>W3C's TPAC is an annual event with five days of meetings (both W3C and WHATWG), many of them joint with wide-review specialists. These are dedicated times to get a lot of people in the same rooms for extended periods.  The availability for hallway conversations also matters a lot: You can corner people there in ways that are much harder when everyone is remote. More progress happens at TPAC than in half the rest of the year combined.</p>
		</section>
	</section>
	<p>Timely coordination — and investment to make it plausible — is still the single biggest problem we face in standards.  I'd love to see us find ways to improve that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Juice]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/Juice.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/Juice.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What's worth the squeeze?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	<h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">The Juice</h1>
	<p class="segue"><em>What's worth the squeeze?</em></p>

	<p>Every day, for both my physical and mental heath, I get away from the computer for a while and for a walk (or two) and listen to some podcast. Sometimes a title suprises me.</p>
	<p>This week's Shop Talk (#687) is a good example. It's titled <a href="https://shoptalkshow.com/687/">"Ben Frain on Responsive Design"</a> and to be honest, I wondered if I'd get anything out of it.  Responsive Design... Haven't we been doing that for... Well, a really long time?  Sure.  And they talk about that.</p>
	<p>But what interested me most was more of a sidequest: There were some "spicy" but thoughtful takes. There was some discussion about which things were actually valuable. And how valuable?  In what ways?  There was discussion about whether some of "the juice was worth the squeeze?"</p>
	<p>Was <code>@scope</code> really worth it?  Is <code>&lt;picture&gt;</code> as valuable as we thought it would be? What about Container Queries? Or <code>@layer</code>? Or are View Transitions too confusing? Or are you actually using <code>:has</code> as much as you imagined?  Honestly, I love hearing some of this discussion from developers because the question isn't "does it have value?" because the answer is "yes, of course".  The questions are more like "At what cost?"  or "Did we have give something else up in order to get that?" or "Do we sometimes try to land a 'quick win' and then come back and really solve the problem, and sort of make it more confusing?"  They are great questions - and reasonable people can disagree!</p>
	<p>Projects like Interop are us trying to do our best to balance lots of inputs and help us make good choices.  Choosing to prioritize something from a list is, inherently, not choosing something else. This year my friend Jake Archibald put together <a href="https://interop-rank.jakearchibald.com/">this prioritization survey tool</a> which lets you try to participate in what is effectively like a step of our process: Order them as you'd personally asign priority if you were in charge. It's hard, and this process is over-simplified in the sense that you are not constrained by the sorts of things real engineering teams are.  Maybe you sort 10 items to the top, but half of them are very expensive and also involve the same expertise.  Maybe that means that realistically we can only pick 2 of those 10, and then we can also pick several more items outside your "top 10".</p>
	<p>There are debatable signals.  Only a few people will pick <code>OffscreenCanvas</code> but most people deal with canvas via only a few primary libraries - so it doesn't take much to lift performance of lots of sites.  MathML isn't going to make you a lot of money - but actually sharing mathematical text is <em>super</em> important.  Or, maybe something seems only mildly valuable, but someone is actually willing to pay for the work to get done.  That changes the calculus about what kind of standards effort it will require from engine stewards themselves.</p>
	<p>And, at the end of the day, in a way, all of us are speculating about perceived value.  The truth is that we often just can't know.  Sometimes, only time will tell.  Sometimes a feature lands flat, only to take off years later.  Sometimes the features we were really excited about turn out to be not so great.</p>
	<p>Once upon a time I imagined a future where the web community did a lot more of this kind of discussion, a lot earlier. I imagined that we should be trying to give people answers in terms of polyfills and origin trials and including their actual feedback with time to use it before we went forward.</p>
	<p>We have done it more than we did, but not nearly as much as I'd hoped.  I still kind of want us to get there.  It means standards might go a little slower sometimes, I guess - but you could get solutions and input faster and have more opportunity for course corrections.</p>
	<p>Anyway, fun episode.  I'd love to hear your critiques too - send them!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Under-investment]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/underinvestment.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/underinvestment.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A lot more words on a short statement I made last week on social media...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
  <h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Under-investment</h1>
  <p class="segue"><em>A lot more words on a short statement I made last week on social media...</em></p>
  <p>A couple of weeks ago I posted on social media that</p>
  <blockquote>
    <p>It never ceases to amaze me how much stuff there is on the web platform that needs more attention than it gets in practice, despite vendors spending tons already.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>Dave Rupert replied asking</p>
  <blockquote> 
    <p>could you itemize that list? i'd be curious. seems like new shiny consumes a lot of the efforts.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>I said "no" at the time because it's true it would be a very long list and exceptionally time consuming task if exhaustive, but... It is probably worth rattling off a bunch that I know more or less off the top of my head from experience - so here goes (in no particular order)... I'll comment on a few:</p>
  <section class="sectioning">
    <h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Big general <em>areas</em>...</h2>
    <p>There are certain areas of focus that just always get shoved to the back burner.</p>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Print</h3>
      <p>It's almost absurd to me that printing and print related APIs have the problems and concerns that they still do given that so much of enterprise and government are web based. For example: Will your images be loaded? Who knows! Did you know there is a <code>.print()</code> and it doesn't act the same in several respects as choosing print from the menu? Shouldn't the browser support many of the CSS based features that print pioneered? Like... paging? Or at least actually investing in considering it in the browser at the same time could have helped us determine if those were even good ideas or shape APIs.</p>
    </section>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Accessibility</h3>
      <p>In theory all of the processes are supposed to help create standards and browsers that are accessible - in practice, we miss on this more often than is comfortable to admit. This is mainly because - for whatever reason - so much of this, from reviews to testing to standards work in designing APIs in the first place, is largely done by volunteers or people disconnected from vendors themselves and just trying to keep up. My colleague Alice Boxhall wrote <a href="https://alice.boxhall.au/articles/a-threat-model-for-accessibility-on-the-web/ ">a piece that touches on this, and more</a>. </p>
    </section>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Internationalization</h3>
      <p>Probably in better shape than accessibility in many ways, but the same basic sorts of things apply here. </p>
    </section>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Testing Infrastructure</h3>
      <p>The amount of things that we are incapable of actually testing is way higher than we should be comfortable with. The web actually spent the first 15 years or so of its life without any actual shared testing like web platform tests. Today, lots and lots of that infrastructure is just Google provided, so not community owned or anything.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section class="sectioning">
    <h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Forgotten tech</h2>
    <p>Then there aere are certain big, important projects that were developed and have been widely deployed for ten, or even close to twenty years at this point, but were maybe a little wonky or buggy and then just sort of walked away from.</p>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">SVG</h3>
      <p>After some (like <a href="https://front-end.social/@AmeliaBR">Amelia</a>) doing amazing work to begin to normalize SVG and CSS, the working group effectively disbanded for years with very little investment from vendors.</p>
    </section>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">MathML</h3>
      <p>From its integration in HTML5 until today, almost none of the work done in browsers has been by the browser vendors themselves. Google is the only vendor who has even joined the working group, and not so much to participate as an org as much as to allow someone interested on their own to participate.</p>
    </section>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Web Speech</h3>
      <p>Google and others were so excited to do this back in (checks watch)... 2012. But they did it too early, and in a community group. It's not even a Recommendation Track thing. I can easily see an argument to be made that this is the result of things swinging pretty far in the other direction - this is more than a decade after W3C had put together the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/voice-intro/">W3C Speech Interface Framework</a> with lots of XML. But meanwhile there is simple and obvious bugs and improvements that can and should be made - there is lots of be rethought here and very little invested from then till now.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section class="sectioning">
    <h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">The "wish list"</h2>
    <p>There is a long list of things that we, as a larger community, aren't investing in in the sense of wider particpation and real funding from browsers, but I think we should... Here are a few of my top ones:</p>
    <section class="sectioning">
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Study of the web (and ability to)</h3>
      <p>The HTTPArchive and chrome status are about the best tools we have, but they're again mainly Google - but even other data sources are biased and incomplete. Until 2019 the study of elements on the web was just running a regexp on home pages in the archive. Until just a year or two ago our study of CSS was kind of similar. It just feels like we should have more here.</p>
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Polyfill ability for CSS</h3>
      <p>A number of us have been saying this for a long time. Even some small things could go a long way here (like, just really exposing what's parsed). After a lot of efforts we got Houdini, which should have helped answer a lot of this. It fizzled out after choosing probably the least interesting first project in my opinion. I don't know that we were looking at it just right, or that we would have done the right things - but I know that not really investing in trying isn't going to get it done either. To be really honest, I'd like a more perfect polyfill story for HTML as well. Once upon a time there was discussion down that road, but when <code>&lt;std-toast&gt;</code>-gate happened, all of the connected discussions died along with it. That's a shame. We <em>are</em> getting there slowly with some important things like custom media queries and so on, but a lot of these things we were starting to pitch a decade ago.</p>
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Protocols</h3>
      <p>The web has thus far been built a very particular way - but there are many ideas (distributed web ideas, for example) which it's very hard for the web to currently adapt toward because it's full of hard problems that really need involvement from vendors. I'd love to see many of those ideas really have an opportunity to take off, but I don't see good evolutionary paths to allow something to really do that. We had some earlier ideas like protocol handlers and content handlers for how this might work. Unfortunately content handlers were removed, and prototcol handlers are extremely limited and incomplete. Trying to imagine how a distributed web could work is pretty difficult with the tools we have. <em>Perhaps</em> part of this is related other items on my list like powerful features or monetization</p>
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">"Web Views" / "Powerful features"</h3>
      <p>A ton of stuff is built with web technology as <em>apps</em> to get around some of the things that are currently difficult security-wide or privacy wise in the browser itself. Maybe that's how it should be, maybe it isn't. I'm not here to say "ship all the fugu stuff" or something, but it it definitely seems silly that there aren't <em>some</em> efforts to even think "above" the browser engines and standardize some APIs, a bit in the vein of what is now the Winter TC. What people are doing today doesn't seem better. I guesss there is a common theme here that I'd like to really invest in finding better ways to let the platform evolve a bit on its own and then pick it up and run with it.</p>
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">"monetization"</h3>
      <p> I mean, this is a really tough one for so many reasons, both tehnical and political, but I just don't see a thing that could have bigger impact than a way to pay creators that isn't limited to ads and a way to fund new ideas. It just seems at the very core of a lot of things. I put it in quotes because I don't mean specifically the proposal called web monetization. There are lots of other ideas and a wide range of attempts happening, some of them seem less directly like money and more like ways to express licencing agreements or earn discounts.</p>
      <h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Maps</h3>
      <p>We seem to have mostly just written off maps entirely as something which you just rely on Google Maps or Apple Maps for. That's a shame because there has been interest at several levels - there was a joint OGC/W3C workshop a few years ago, and many ideas. Almost all of them would benefit more than just those few proprietary map systems. There are even simple primitive ideas like adding the concept of pan and zoom to the platform, maybe in CSS. <em>Surely</em> we can do better than where things are right now, but who is going to invest to get it there?</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section class="sectioning"> 
    <h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">There's a long list</h2>
    <p>There's way more things we could list here... Drag and drop needs work and improvements. Editing (see Contenteditable/execCommand/EditContext) is terribly hard. Given the importance, you'd think it would be one of the bigger areas of investment, but it's not really. Hit testing is a big area that needs defining. I mean, you can see that this year we got <a href="https://github.com/web-platform-tests/interop/issues?q=is%3Aissue%20state%3Aopen%20label%3Afocus-area-proposal">134 focus area proposals for Interop 2026</a>. Those aren't all areas that are under-invested in, exactly, but whatever we choose to focus on there is time and budget we can't spend on the things in this list...</p>
    <p>In the past, I might have said documentation, but I feel like were just doing a lot better with that. We also now have the collectively funded, transparent and independent <a href="https://openwebdocs.org/">openwebdocs.org</a> which Igalia has helped fund since its inception and, to my mind, is one of the most positive things. So many things on this list even <em>could</em> take a similar approach. It would be great to see.</p>
  </section>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Web Bucks]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/WebBucks.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/WebBucks.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Back in September 2024 I wrote a piece about the history of attempts at standardizing some kind of Micropayments going back to the late 90s. Like a lot of things I write, it's the outcome of looking at history and background for things that I'm actively thinking about. An announcement the other day made me think that perhaps now is a good time for a follow up post.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
  <h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Web Bucks</h1>
  <p class="segue">Back in September 2024 I wrote a piece about the <a href="https://bkardell.com/blog/MicropaymentsHistory.html">history of attempts at standardizing some kind of Micropayments going back to the late 90s</a>. Like a lot of things I write, it's the outcome of looking at history and background for things that I'm actively thinking about. An announcement the other day made me think that perhaps now is a good time for a follow up post.</p>
  <p>As you probably already know if you're reading this, I write and think a lot about the health of the web ecosystem. We've even got a whole <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nsej-VSS9aI&amp;list=PL_BRVuWxk8spg9XL-XUPSptJNrC6y3y9e">playlist of videos (lots of podcast episodes) on the topic</a> on YouTube. Today, that's nearly all paid for, on all sides, by advertising. In several important respects, it's safe to say that the status quo is under many threats. In several ways it's also worth questioning if the status quo is even <em>good</em>.</p>
  <p>When Ted Nelson first imagined Micropayments in the 1960s, he was imaging a fair economic model for digital publishing. We've had many ideas and proposals since then. Web Monetization is one idea which isn't dead yet. Its main ideas involve embedding a declarative link to a "payment pointer" (like a wallet address) where payments can be sent via Interledger. I say "sent", but "streamed" might be more accurate. Interledger is a novel idea which treats money as "packets" and routes small amounts around. Full disclosure: Igalia has been working on some prototype work in Chromium to help see what a native implementation would look like, what its architecture would be and what options this opens (or closes). Our work has been funded by the Interledger Foundation. It does not amount to an endorsement, and it does not mean something will ship. That said, it doesn't mean the opposite either. </p>
  <p>You might know that Brave, another Chromium-based browser, has system for creators too. In their model, publishers/creators sign up and verify their domain (or social accounts!), and people browsing those with Brave browsers sort of keep track of that locally, and at the end of the month Brave can batch up and settle accounts of Basic Attention Tokens ("BAT") which they can then pay out to creators in lump sums. As of the time of this writing, Brave has 88 million monthly active users (<a href="https://brave.com/transparency/">source</a>) who could be paying its 1.67 million plus content creators and publishers (<a href="https://creators.brave.com/">source</a>).</p>
  <p>Finally, in India, UPI offers most transactions free of charge and can also be used for micro payments - it's being used in $240 billion USD / month worth of transactions!</p>
  <p>But there's also some "adjacent" stuff that doesn't claim to be micro transactions but somehow are similar:</p>
  <p>If you've ever used Microsoft's Bing search engine, they also give you "points" (I like to call them "Bing Bucks") which you can trade in for other stuff (the payment is going in a different direction!). There was also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scroll_(web_service)">Scroll</a>, years ago, which was aimed to be a kind of <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/1/29/21113003/scroll-subscription-service-publisher-web-cookie-hack">universal service you could pay into to remove ads on many properties</a> (it was bought by Twitter and shut down.)</p>
  <section class="sectioning">
    <h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Enter: Offerwall</h2>
    <p>Just the other day, Google Ad Manager gave a new idea a potentially <em>really</em> signficant boost. I think it's worth looking at: <a href="https://blog.google/products/ads-commerce/offerwall-gives-publishers-more-options-audiences-more-control/">Offerwall</a>. Offerwall lets sites provide potentially <em>a few</em> ways to monetize content, and for users to choose the one that they prefer. For example, a publisher can set up to allow reading their site in exchange for watching an ad (similar to YouTube's model). That's pretty interesting, but far more interesting to me, is that it integrates with a third-party service called <a href="https://www.supertab.co/faq">Supertab</a>. Supertab lets people provide their own subscriptions - including a tiny fee for this page, or access to the site for some timed pass - 4 hours, 24 hours, a week, etc. It does this with pretty friction-less wallet integration and by 'pooling' the funds until it makes sense to do a real, regular transaction. Perhaps the easiest thing is to <a href="https://www.supertab.co/examples">look at some of their own examples</a>.</p>
    <p>Offerwall also allows other integrations, so maybe we'll see some of these begin to come together somehow too.</p>
    <p>It's a very interesting way to split the difference and address a few complaints of micro transaction critics and generally people skeptical that something could gain significant traction. More than that even, it seems to me that by integrating with Google Ad manager it's got about as much advantage as anyone could get (the vast majority of ads are already served with Google Ad manager and this actually tries to expand that).</p>
  </section>
  <p>I'm <em>very</em> keen to see how this all plays out! What do you think will happen? Share your thoughts with me on <a href="https://bkardell.com/links">social media</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Houdini Re-Revisted]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/HoudiniReRe.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/HoudiniReRe.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Recent presentations at BlinkOn strike some familliar notes. Seems a common theme, ideas come back.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ 
  <h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Houdini Re-Revisted</h1>
  <p class="segue">Recent presentations at BlinkOn strike some familliar notes. Seems a common theme, ideas come back.</p>
  <p>Since I joined Igalia in 2019, I don't think I've missed a BlinkOn. This year, however, there was a conflict with the W3C AC meetings and we felt that it was more useful that I attend those, since Igalia already had a sizable contingent at BlinkOn itself and my <a href="https://youtu.be/ptXY45HlQ6U">Web History talk with Chris Lilley</a> was pre-recorded. </p>

  <p>When I returned, and videos of the event began landing, I was keen to see what people talked about. There were lots of interesting talks, but one jumped out at me right away: Bramus gave one called "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=njdiu83do0M">CSS Parser Extensions</a>" - which I wasn't familliar with, so was keen to see. Turns out it was just very beginnings of him exploring ideas to make CSS polyfillable. </p>

  <p>This talk made me sit up and pay attention because, actually, it's really how I came to be involved in standards. It's the thing that started a lot of the conversations that eventually became the Extensible Web Community Group and the <a href="https://extensiblewebmanifesto.org">Extensible Web Manifesto</a>, and ultimately <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sE3ttkP15f8">Houdini</a>, a joint Task Force of the W3C TAG and CSS Working Group (in fact, I am also the one who proposed the name ✨). In his talk, he hit on many of the same notes that led me there too.</p>

  <p>Polyfills are really interesting when you step back and look at them. They can be used to make the standards development, feedback and rollout so much better. But CSS is almost historically hostile to that approach becauase it just throws away anything it doesn't understand. That means if you want to polyfill something you've got to re-implement lots of stuff that the browser already does: You've got to re-fetch the stylesheet (if you can!) as text, and then bring your own parser to parse it, and then... well, you still can't actually realistically implement many things.</p>

  <p>But what if you could?</p>

  <p>Houdini has stalled. In my mind, this mainly due to <em>when</em> it happened and <em>what it chose to focus on shipping first</em>. One of the first things that we all agreed to in the first Houdini meeting was that we expose the parser. This is true for all of the reasons Bramus discussed, and more. But that effort got hung up on the fact that there was a sense we first needed a typed OM. I'm not sure how true that really is. Other cool Houdini things were, I think, also hung up on lots of things that were being reworked at the time, and resource competition. But I think that the thing that really <em>killed it</em> was just what shipped first. It was not something that might be really useful for polyfilling, like custom functions or custom media queries or custom pseduo classes, or very ambitiously, something like custom layouts --- but custom paint. The CSS Working Group doesn't publish a lot of new "paints". There are approximately 0 named background images, for example.  There's no <code>background-image: checkerboard;</code> for example.  But the working group does publish lots of those other things like functions or psueudo classes. See what I mean? Those other things were part of the real vision - they can be used to make cow paths. Or, they can be used to show that, actually, nobody wants that cow path. Or, if it isn't - It can instead rapidly inspire better solutions..</p>

  <p>Anyway, the real challenge with most polyfills is performance. Any time that we're going to step out of "60 fps scrollers" into JS land that's iffy... But not impossible, and if we're honest, we'd have to admit that the truth is that our current/actual attempts to polyfill are definitely worse than something <em>closer</em> to native. With effort, surely we can at least improve things by looking at where there are some nice "joints" where we can cleave the problem.</p>
  <p>This is why in recent years I've suggested that perhaps what would really benefit us is a few custom things (like functions) and then just enabling CSS-like languages, which can handle the fetch/parse problems and perhaps give us some of the most basic primitive ideas.</p>
  <p>So, where will all of this go? Who knows - but I'm glad some others are interested and talking about some of it again. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Operation]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/Operation.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/Operation.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Some short thoughts on recent antitrust and the future of the web platform...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
  <h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Operation</h1>
<p class="segue">Some short thoughts on recent antitrust and the future of the web platform...</p>

<p>Last week, in a <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25900111-google-ad-antitrust-ruling/">115 page US Antitrust ruling</a> a federal judge in Virginia found that Google had  <em>two more</em> monopolies, this time with relation to advertising technolgies.  Previously, you'll recall that we had rulings related to search.  There are still more open cases related to Android.  And it's not <em>only</em> in the US that similar actions are playing out.</p>
<p>All of these cases kind of mention one another because the problems themselves are all deeply intertwined - but this one is really at the heart of it: That sweet, sweet ad money. I think that you could argue, reasonably, that pretty much everything else was somehow in service of that.  </p>
<p>Initially, they made a ton of money showing ads <em>every time someone searches</em>, and pretty quickly signed a default search deal with Mozilla to drive the number of searches way up.</p>
<p>Why make a browser of your own?  To drive the searches that show the ads, but also keep more of the money.</p>
<p>Why make OSes of your own, and deals around things that need to be installed? To guarantee that all of those devices drive the searches to show the ads.</p>
<p>And so on...</p>
<p>For a long time now, I've been trying to discuss what, to me, is a rather worrying problem: That those default search dollars are, in the end, what funds the whole web ecosystem.  Don't forget that it's not <em>just</em> about the web itself, it's about the platform which provides the underlying technology for just about everything else at this point too.  </p>
<p>Between years of blog posts, a <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_BRVuWxk8spg9XL-XUPSptJNrC6y3y9e&amp;feature=shared">podcast series</a>, several talks, experiments like <a href="https://bkardell.com/blog/OpenPrioritization.html">Open Prioritization</a> I have been thinking about this <em>a lot</em>.  Untangling it all is going to be quite complex. </p>
<p>In the US, the governments proposed remedies touch just about every part of this.  I've been trying to think about how I could sum up my feelings and concerns, but it's quite complex.  Then, the other day <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/04/chrome-on-the-chopping-block-as-googles-search-antitrust-trial-moves-forward/?utm_source=bsky&amp;utm_medium=social">an article on arstechnica</a> contained an illustration which seemed pretty perfect..</p>
<figure class="captioned-image">
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/google-monoperation-game-2048x1152.jpg">
    <figcaption>A "game" board that looks like the game Operation, but instead of pieces of internal anatomy there are logos for chrome, gmail, ads, adsense, android and on the board it says "Monoperation: Skill game where you are the DOJ" and the person is removing chrome, and a buzzer is going ff</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This image (credited to Aurich Lawson) kind of hit the nail on its head for me: I deeply hope they will be absoltely <em>surgical</em> about this intervention, because the patient I'm worried about isn't Google, it's the whole Web Platform.</p>

<p class="note">
  If this is interesting to you, my colleague Eric Meyer and I posted an Igalia Chats podcast episode on the topic: <a href="https://www.igalia.com/chats/adpocalypseNow">Adpocalypse Now?</a>
</p>

]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Breakouts 2025: Collective]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/Breakouts2025.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/Breakouts2025.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The other day was W3C Breakouts Day: Effectively, an opportunity for people to create sessions to talk about or work on anything related to the Web.  We do this twice a year.  Once entirely virtually (last week) and then again during hybrid meetings in association with W3C's biggest event of the year, called "TPAC".]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	<h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Breakouts 2025: Collective</h1>
<p class="segue">The other day was <a href="https://www.w3.org/2025/03/breakouts-day-2025/">W3C Breakouts Day</a>: Effectively, an opportunity for people to create sessions to talk about or work on anything related to the Web.  We do this twice a year.  Once entirely virtually (last week) and then again during hybrid meetings in association with W3C's biggest event of the year, called "TPAC".</p>

<p>This year there were 4 blocks of sessions with 4-5 sessions competing concurrently for the same time slot. There were 2 in the morning that I'd chosen, but then realized that I had calendar conflicts with other meetings and wound up missing them.</p>

<p>In the afternoon there were 3 sessions proposed by Igalians - unfortunately two of them simulteneously:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/w3c/breakouts-day-2025/issues/12">Vectors of Neglect</a> - about SVG, led by Eric Meyer.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/w3c/breakouts-day-2025/issues/14">Revisiting in-band text tracks in MediaSource Extensions</a>, led by Alicia Boya Garcia</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/w3c/breakouts-day-2025/issues/11">Collective funding, governance and prioritization of a browser engine projects</a>, led by myself and Stephanie Stimac</li>
</ul>
<p>There were actually several in that timeslot that I wanted to attend but the choice was pretty straightforward: I'd attend mine and Eric's. Unfortunately I did a bad job chairing and forgot to assign a scribe or record a presentation.</p>

<p>Eric's session told the story of SVG and how, despite it getting a lot of love from developers and designers and other working group participants, it just didn't get a lot of love or investment from the browser vendors themselves. Amelia Belamy-Royd's (former editor/chair) told us about how things ultimately stalled out around 2020 with so much left undone, burnout, disappointments, and a W3C working group that was almost closed up with a note last year before being sort of "rescued" at the last minute with a very targeted rechartering. However, that rechartering still hasn't resulted in much - no new meetings, etc. We talked about how Igalia has been investing, along with companies like Wix, in trying to help move things forward. Then the question was: How can we move it forward, together? You can read <a href="https://www.w3.org/2025/03/26-svg-neglect-minutes.html">the minutes</a> for more, but one idea was a collective around SVG.</p>

<p>I mention this because while might they <em>seem</em> at first like pretty different topics, Eric's session and my own are really just two things raising the same overarching question: <em>Why have we built the infrastructure of the whole web ecosystem to be fundamentally dependent on the funding and prioritization of a few private organizations?</em>. And - <em>how can we fix that?</em>.</p>

<p>My session presented some things we've done, or tried so far.</p>

<section class="sectioning">
	<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Things we're trying...</h2>
	<p>First, just moving from proprietary projects to open source has helped a bit.  Instead of one organization being 100% responsible, the stewards themselves today contribute "only" ~80 to 95% of the commits.</p>

	<div style="display: grid; grid-template-columns: 1fr 1fr 1fr;">
      <img src="/media/2023/moz.svg" style="width: 100%" title="mozilla-central - mozilla contributed 87.2% of commits">
      <img src="/media/2023/apple-webkit.svg" style="width: 100%" title="webkit - apple contributed 78.1% of commits">
      <img src="/media/2023/google-chrome.svg" style="width: 100%" title="chromium - google committed 95.5% of commits">
    </div>


	<p>My company Igalia is among the top few committers to all of the web engine projects every year for at least half a decade, and we have many ways that we try to diversify work upstream. What's interesting about attempts to diversify funding is that there is a kind of a spectrum here relating to both the scope of what we're tackling and how well understood the approach is...</p>

	<div class="spectrum">
		<span>one sponsor/single issue</span>
		<span>collective/whole project</span>
	</div>
	
	<p>On the left is a single sponsor with very specific/measurable tasks. This could be a list of bugs, or implementation of a pretty stable feature in a single engine. You can contract Igalia for stuff like this - The <code>:has()</code> implementation and proof-of-concept that moved the needle in Chromium, for example, was sponsored by EyeO. CSS Grid in Blink and WebKit was sponsored by Bloomberg Tech. <em>We know how to do this</em>. We've got lots of practice.</p>

	<p>Moving slightly more 'right', we have things like our <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2020/07/crowdfunding-web-platform-features-open-prioritization/">Open Priortization</a> which is trying to decide how to prioritize and share a funding burden. We know less of how to do this, we learned things with the experiment, but we've not repeated it because it involved a lot of "extra" work.</p>

	<p>Then there's our efforts with MathML, funded by grants, then partnerships, then a collective aimed at generally advancing and maintaining MathML support in browsers.  That's now involving more decision making - there's not a tight list of tasks or even a specific browser.  You need to take in money to find out how much budget you have, and then try to figure out how to use it.  In this case, there's a steering committee made up of the biggest funders. Every 6 months or so there is a <a href="https://opencollective.com/mathml-core-support/updates/mathml-h1-report-2024">report of the work that was done submitted for payment</a>. Is that a great model?</p>
	

	<p>We also have Wolvic, which attempted to have partnerships and a collective, with a model where if you put in a kind of minimum amount every 6 months then you would get invited to a town hall to discuss how we'd prioritize the spending of available funds.  Is that a great model?  The thing I like about it is that it binds things to some kind of reality. It's great if someone gave $500, for example, but if 10 other orgs also did so and they all want different things, none of which we can do with the available funds... At least they can all help decide what to do.  In that model, the input is still only informative - it's ultimately Igalia who decides.</p>
	
	<p>Or, you might have seen a new thing hosted at the Linux Foundation for <a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/press/linux-foundation-announces-the-launch-of-supporters-of-chromium-based-browsers">funding work in Chromium</a>.  That's more formal, but kind of similar in challenges. Unfortunately there was no one attending our sessions who could talk about it - I know a bit more, but I'm not going to break news on my blog :). We'll have a podcast about it when we can.</p>
	
	<p>Or, a little further right there's <a href="https://openwebdocs.org">Open Web Docs (OWD)</a>, which I'm pleased <em>does</em> seem to be succeeding at sponsoring some real work and doing real prioritization.  Florian from OWD was there and was able to give us some real thoughts.  They too are drawing now from grants like Soverign Tech Fund.  They produce as part of this an <a href="https://openwebdocs.org/content/reports/2024/">Impact Report</a>.</p>

	<p>Or, maybe all the way to the right you have a general browser fund like <a href="https://servo.org/sponsorship/">Servo</a>.  There it is the Technical Steering Committee that decides what to do with the funds.</p>

	<p>A lot of this thinking is currently still pretty esoteric because, for example, through the <em>collective</em>, Servo isn't taking in enough money for even a single full time employee. I also mentioned our work with Interop, and the fact that even with that level of effort to priortize, it is very difficult to not wind up taking resources away from actual work in order to figure out which work to potentially do! It's hard to not add admin costs that eat away at the overall progress. But that's exactly why we should be talking about these things now. How can we make this work?</p>
</section>

<section class="sectioning">
	<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">The Actual Discussion</h2>
	<p>As I said, we didn't have a scribe, but there was some discussion I can attempt to summarize from the queue I can still see in IRC.</p>

	<section class="q sectioning">
		<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Q. Do you think the W3C has a role to play?</h3>
		<p>That's why I brought it here. My own <em>desire</em> would be yes.  There are some venues where working groups and interest groups are encouraged to pool funds and so on - but the W3C isn't currently one of them and I'm unsure how others feel. It's a thing I have been trying to pitch for a few years now that we could figure out.</p>
		
		<p>The Wolvic model that I described above was born from thoughts around this. What if W3C groups had the ability to put money into a common fund and then at the end of the year they could decide how to deploy it. Maybe sometimes that would be for tools. Maybe sometimes that would be for fixing bugs. Maybe sometimes that would be for new implementation, or last implementation, or supporting spec authorship. But it would always be grounded on something real about collaboration that puts at <em>some</em> degree of power beyond the implementers. Maybe that would mean that print CSS would inch along at a snail's pace - but at least it's better than not at all, and it shows a way. At least it doesn't seem like the group isn't even picking up the phone.</p>

	</section>

	<section class="q sectioning">
		<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Q. Are engines like Servo and Ladybird filing implementation reports? WPT?</h3>

		<p>Basically... Not exactly. The main thrust is that both engines <em>do</em> make themselves available on Web Platform Tests and closely track their scores. That said, the models differ quite a bit in their approach and Ladybird, for example, generally is more focused from the outside in. It's possible they only start with 25% of the standard required to load a certain page. So, at what point would they submit an impact report? Both projects <em>do</em> currently open issues when they find implementation related questions or problems, and both have the ability to expand the test suites in response to those issues. So, effectively: Nobody has time for that level of formality, but they're following the spirit of it.</p>
	</section>

	<section class="q sectioning">
		<h3 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 3rem;">Q. Doesn't it help to have a thing you can measure if you approach someone to ask for money?</h3>

		<p>Yes, that is the whole point of my spectrum above. The further right you move, the more of a question this is. On our podcast, for example, we've asked people "Why don't you donate to Mozilla?" and the main answer given is always "I don't know what they'll spend it on, but probably not things I would agree with".  The more people putting in, the more there is to balance or require trust. Currently a lot of these work for grants or more specific/finite problems which do reports of success - like the one I provided above for MathML or the implementation report in OWD.</p>

		<p>But does it mean there <em>shouldn't</em> be more general funds?  Currently the general funds come from default search and wind up with a single org to decide - is it what we want?</p>
	</section>
</section>
	<p>So, that's all that was discussed. All in all, it was pretty good - but I'm slightly disappointed there wasn't a little more discussion of how we could collectively govern or priortize, or even if we all agreed that that's something that we want.  I'd love to hear any of your thoughts! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[11ty Math]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/11tyMath.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/11tyMath.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Markdown, LaTex and ASCII - who writes HTML?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	<h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">11ty Math</h1>
	<p class="segue">Markdown, LaTex and ASCII - who writes HTML?</p>
	<script src="../prism.js"></script>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="../prism.css">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fred-wang.github.io/MathFonts/STIX/mathfonts.css">
    
	<p>Very nearly none of the content that we encounter online is entirely hand authored from opening doctype to closing HTML tag - it's assembled.  We have layouts, and includes and templates and so on.  And, most of the actual <em>content</em> that we produce and consume is written in some more familiar or easier to write shorthand.  For most of the people reading this, it's probably mostly markdown.</p>

	<p>But did you know that lots of the places that you use markdown <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/get-started/writing-on-github/working-with-advanced-formatting/writing-mathematical-expressions">like GitHub</a> and GitLab, and <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/languages/markdown">Visual Studio</a> support embedding mathematical expressions written in LaTex surrounded by <code>$</code> (inline) or <code>$$</code> (block)? Those are then transformed for you to rendered Math with MathML?</p>

	<p>It got me thinking that we should have a kind of similarly standard easy setup for 11ty.  It would be a huge win to process it on the server, MathML will render natively, fast, without FOUC. It will be accessible, styleable, scale appropriately with text-size and zoom and so on.</p>

	<p>The super interesting thing to note about most of the tools where you can use markup is that so many of them are built on common infrastructure: <a href="https://github.com/markdown-it/markdown-it">markdown-it</a>.  The architectural pattern of markdown-it allows people to write plugins, and if you're looking to match those above, you can do it pretty easily with the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@mdit/plugin-katex">@mdit/plugin-katex</a>:

	</p><pre><code class="language-javascript">/* eleventy.config.js */
const markdownIt = require("markdown-it");

module.exports = async function (eleventyConfig) {

  const { katex } = (await import("@mdit/plugin-katex"));
  eleventyConfig.setLibrary(
  	"md", 
  	markdownIt().use(katex, {output: "mathml"})
  );

}</code></pre>

	<p>And... That's it.  Now you can embed LaTex math in your markdown just as you can in those other places and it will do the work of generating fast, native, accessible, and styleable MathML...

	</p><pre><code class="language-html">Some math  $\frac{x^2}{a^2} + \frac{y^2}{b^2} = 1$ whee.</code></pre>

	<p>Yields...</p>
	<pre><code class="language-html">&lt;p&gt;Some math <span class="katex">&lt;math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"&gt;&lt;semantics&gt;&lt;mrow&gt;&lt;mfrac&gt;&lt;msup&gt;&lt;mi&gt;x&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;2&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;/msup&gt;&lt;msup&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;2&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;/msup&gt;&lt;/mfrac&gt;&lt;mo&gt;+&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mfrac&gt;&lt;msup&gt;&lt;mi&gt;y&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;2&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;/msup&gt;&lt;msup&gt;&lt;mi&gt;b&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;2&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;/msup&gt;&lt;/mfrac&gt;&lt;mo&gt;=&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mn&gt;1&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;/mrow&gt;&lt;annotation encoding="application/x-tex"&gt;\frac{x^2}{a^2} + \frac{y^2}{b^2} = 1&lt;/annotation&gt;&lt;/semantics&gt;&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/span&gt; whee.&lt;/p&gt;</span></code></pre>

	<p>Which your browser renders as...</p>

	<div class="example">
		<p>Some math inline <span class="katex"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mfrac><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><msup><mi>a</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><msup><mi>y</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><msup><mi>b</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\frac{x^2}{a^2} + \frac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</annotation></semantics></math></span> whee.</p>
	</div>

	<p>Surrounding the math part alone with <code>$$</code> instead yields block math, which renders as..</p>

	<p class="katex-block"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block"><semantics><mrow><mfrac><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><msup><mi>a</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><msup><mi>y</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><msup><mi>b</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\frac{x^2}{a^2} + \frac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</annotation></semantics></math></p>


	<div class="note">
  	Mathematical fonts are critical for rendering.  We <strong>almost</strong> have universally good default math fonts, but <strong>some</strong> operating systems (eyes Android disapprovingly) still don't.  However, like me you can include some CSS to help. On this page I've included 
  	<pre><code class="language-html">&lt;link  href="https://fred-wang.github.io/MathFonts/STIX/mathfonts.css" /&gt;</code></pre>.
  	<br> You can <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/MathML/Authoring#mathematical_fonts">read a lot more about this on MDN</a>. 


	</div>


	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">AsciiMath Math / Mathup</h2>
		<p>While LaTeX is by far the most common way that people author math, there are people who prefer AsciiMath.  Rúnar Berg Baugsson Sigríðarson (<a href="https://github.com/runarberg">@runarberg</a>) has a nice <a href="https://runarberg.github.io/mathup/#why-not-tex">explanation as to why they prefer to not use TeX</a>.</p>

		<p>His mathup package seems pretty nice (an AsciiMath dialect more than just AsciiMath), and there is also a corresponding  <a href="https://github.com/runarberg/markdown-it-math">markdown-it-math</a> which is similarly easy to use...</p>

	<pre><code class="language-javascript">/* eleventy.config.js */
const markdownIt = require("markdown-it");

module.exports = async function (eleventyConfig) {
  const markdownItMath = 
  	(await import('markdown-it-math')).default;

  eleventyConfig.setLibrary(
    "md", 
    markdownIt().use(markdownItMath)
  );
}</code></pre>
	
	<p>Then, you can embed AsciiMath in your markdown, fenced by the same <code>$</code> or <code>$$</code> and it will generate some nice MathML. For example...</p>

	<pre><code class="language-html">$$
e = sum_(n=0)^oo 1/n!
$$</code></pre>


	<p>Will be transformed at build time and render in your browser as...</p>

	<math display="block"><mi>e</mi><mo>=</mo><munderover><mo>∑</mo><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow><mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mi></munderover><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac></math>

	<p class="note">Make sure you get markdown-it-math 5.0.0-rc.0 or above or this won't work.  You might also consider including <a href="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mathup/dist/mathup.css">their stylesheet</a>.</p>

	<p class="note">markdown-it-math also supports a nice pattern for easily integrating other engines for embedded transformations like Ron Kok's <a href="https://temml.org/">Temml</a> or Fred Wang's <a href="https://fred-wang.github.io/TeXZilla/">TeXZilla</a>.</p>

	</section>


	<section class="sectioning">
		<h2 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2.5rem;">Unicode Math</h2>
		<p>There is also Unicode Math, which Murray Sargent III developed and had integrated into all of the Microsoft products.  It's pretty nifty too if you ask me. This repo has a nice <a href="https://github.com/MurrayIII/UnicodeMathML/tree/main?tab=readme-ov-file#how-does-its-syntax-compare-to-asciimath-latex-and-mathml">comparison of the three</a>.</p>

		<p>Unfortunately there is no npm module for it (<a href="https://github.com/doersino/UnicodeMathML/issues/5">yet</a>), so for now, unfortunately that remains an open wish.</p> 
	</section>

	<p>So, that's it.  Enjoy.  Mathify your static sites.</p>

	<p class="note">Before you go... The work of Math rendering in browsers is <em>severely</em> under funded.  Almost none of the effort or funding over the last 30 years to make this possible has come from browser vendors, but rather from individual contributors and those willing to help fund them.  If you appreciate the importance of this work, please consider helping to <a href="https://opencollective.com/mathml-core-support">support the work</a> with a small monthly donation, and please help us to publicly lobby implementers to invest in it.</p>

]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Link in Bio]]></title>
            <link>https://bkardell.com/blog/LinkInBio.html</link>
            <guid>https://bkardell.com/blog/LinkInBio.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Embracing an IndieWeb thing...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
  <h1 class="contextual-heading" style="font-size: 2rem;">Link in Bio</h1>
  <p class="segue">Embracing an IndieWeb thing...</p>

  <p>Over the years, I've been there as things have come and gone on the interwebs. I had accounts on AIM, MySpace, Blogger, FaceBook, WordPress, Google Plus, Twitter, Instagram, and plenty more.  On each one, I wind up with a profile where I want to link people to other places I am online - and those places don't always make it easy to do that.  So, something short and memorable that you could even type if you had to is ideal - like a handle: @briankardell or @bkardell or, in the end: bkardell.com is pretty great.</p>

  <p>Back in 2016, some folks felt the same frustration and instead created this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linktree">Linktree</a> thing.  But... It's just like, a fremium thing that gives you <em>the most basic single page website ever</em>?  Yes, and today they have 50 million users and are valued at $1.3 billion - that's a value of $26/user. I mean, I found that amazing.</p>

  <p>But, here's the thing: After a while I realized that there's something to it.  Not the business model, specifically, but the link in bio idea.  The link in bio is generally not a great website on its own, but it's a page where people can pretty quickly navigate to the thing they're looking for without other noise or fluff.  Which is something that a home page often isn't.  So,  I've learned to really appreciate them, actually.</p>

  <p>Back in about 2020, some IndieWeb folks began <a href="https://indieweb.org/Linktree">thinking about, criticizing and brainstorming around it too</a>.  They began writing about <a href="https://indieweb.org/link_in_bio">Link in Bio</a>, and why it might be useful to have your own version.  There are several examples of people doing something similar.</p>

  <p>Recently a bunch of things smashed together in my mind.  First, on ShopTalk, I heard Chris and Dave talking about "<a href="https://shoptalkshow.com/647/">slash pages</a>" (pages right off the root domain with <a href="https://slashpages.net/">well known names</a>).  Second, I've been working on social media plans - getting away from some platforms and moving to others and thinking about these problems.  An IndieWeb style `/links` page, that adds <code>rel="me"</code> links is a really nice, simple way to achieve a whole lot of things if we'd all adopt it - not the least of which is that it's an evergreen link, almost as simple as a handle, to where people can find you should you choose to leave...</p>

  <p>So, starting with me, and Igalia, you can find our links at <a href="https://bkardell.com/links">bkardell.com/links</a> and <a href="https://igalia.com/links">igalia.com/links</a> respectively.</p>

  <figure class="captioned-image">
    <img src="/media/2025/bye.png">
    <figcaption>A screenshot of Igalia's post with a sunset and birds flying away, linking to our /links page</figcaption>
  </figure>


]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>